So we started looking at off policy Monte
Carlo methods in the last class, right and
let us continue from there, so people remember
important sampling, yes I said something like
expected value of what is the, right so expected
value of f(x) where is x is sampled according
to p can be given by expected value of f(x).p(x)/q(x)
where f is sample from q, I mean x is sample
from q, okay so this is the basic area been
an important sampling and we saw some expression
for it, so which was essentially so notice
that there is no approximation here, right.
So this is approximation we do 1/n right,
we also wrote another sampler which was okay,
so this is the I think this is called the
weighted
important sampling estimated right, this is
a weighted important sampling or normalize
right, so different ways in which people calling,
okay. so how are we going to use it in Monte
Carlo learning so what are the samples we
are talking here, what is our f(xi) what is
xi what is f(xi) right, and what is p(xi)
and q(xi) what are these quantities in a Monte
Carlo setting.
Start with the x, exactly it is the trajectory
where you saw doubtful about it if you say
trajectory yeah, okay good. Well, I am happy
nobody said it depends because it does not
okay, so in this case xi is the trajectory
and so you are drawing samples you are drawing
trajectories so what f(xi), the return right
f(xi) is a return on the trajectory, okay.
Now what is p(xi), little bit more, little
bit more you have to related xi, right probability
of the trajectory given that I am following
policy p, right.
So p(xi) is a probability of the trajectory
xi given that I am following the policy p
according to which, for which I am trying
to do the evaluation, okay. So what will be
q(xi) probability of the trajectory under
the policy that I am actually following, okay
so for to sinking up with the text book case
we will p is the policy that you are interested
in and µ is the policy that you are following,
okay sometimes it is called the behavior policy.
.
So let us say xi is some trajectory okay,
so x is some trajectory which starts of with
some state s0 right, what will I do after
that right, so that will be a trajectory correct.
So there is some, so what will be the probability
what will be the p(xi) so in fact I can leave
out the rs because they will be captured in
the f part, right so I can actually ignore
I mean the r are there, right but when I am
computing the probability of xi I can ignore
the r parts, because they will be captured
in the f, okay.
So I must put them back here, yeah so what
is the probability of xi what it will look
like, p(a0) it will looks like a q, a0 given
s0(p(s1)) given s0,a0 into anything else,
right so
I need a some probability that I will start
with s0 okay, that is the USL thing, is it
fine, okay. So what will be q(xi) right, so
can you compute p(xi) trick question. I need
the ps right, I do not know the p I mean the
whole idea behind going to Monte Carlo methods
is we do not want the ps right, likewise exactly
but if you think about it where we need p
is only as a ratio with q.
So I never need to compute p and q separately
all I need to do is compute the ratio so if
I take the ratio what happens it reduces to,
right if I can write this as a product of
the ratios that is fine, so I think that might
been easier way of doing it, so I mean historically
I mean p is used for both the product as well
as the policy so please this ambiguity on
context, okay it is clear. So now I know how
to find the ratio p(xi)/q(xi) so would this
kind be then, so if you think about it little
tricky I should not have used i here I apologies,
really apologies.
Okay, we have i on the left hand side I should
not have use i as the running variable, sorry
okay, so what do we have here, so what is
this correspond to what does it weighted important
sample here correspond to the expected value
of f(x) right, so what is that, what is that
value function right, so the value function
of some state right, vp(s) right some s, right.
So essentially we have now vp(s) is equal
to, so let us put a super script in brackets
i to denote that this quantities come from
the ith trajectory, right.
So this i=1 to n means I am running n different
trajectories so I put this super script to
denote that they are coming from the ith trajectory
and the return is computed starting from state
s, okay so likewise I mean I need to have
a thing here, so
is that fine, so this is how I will do Monte
Carlo policy evaluation, okay in off policy
fashion, okay. So why do I want to into off
policy learning right, so this is allow me
to explore lot of lot more states right, then
if I am following policy p so I can get larger
samples of states values estimated and so
on and so forth.
And it can also be that maybe view and so
easier exploration policy than what I have
with p I am trying to sampling from so that
could be variety of reasons well I want to
do this and I encourage all of you to read
the text book, right and yeah I miss something
in the denominator I need a big p thanks,
right I just indicative here all know what
I missed there, so just filled in, okay. So
there were few tricks that they do in their
book they take this and convert this into
an incremental method where you can keep I
mean you do not have to wait till if you finish
running the trajectory to compute this importance
weight.
You can keep updating it as we go along right
and then you can keep updating this estimate
also as you go along in the trajectory you
do not have to remember everything right,
so they give you all kinds of small arithmetic
tricks to make it incremental right, so again
I encourage all of you to look it up right,
if you are going to ever implement a Monte
Carlo method that is the way you will do it
not like this, right so I am really, really
trying to get you guys to read the book, right.
So somebody other than Sekhar I mean try to
guilt him into reading the book yeah, anyway
great, so this is all fine for evaluation
so what do you do for control is there anything
else you have to be careful about for control.
What said, yeah so how will it change, how
will this change for first visit and every
visit, will it change, we need action values
so what is the problem with using action values
there is any specific problem if receiver
using action values, okay.
So I am going to integrate actually go read
the book, okay I am not going to tell you
just go read the book and figure out how would
you do off policy Monte Carlo control, okay.